Okay, we are now going to, okay, we're going to call to order this ready to the meeting of the Miami City Council
for today's day. Item two is public and
excuse me, input on scheduled personal periods is the only audience that was just to adjust the council on any of the agenda.
You're being done, item three is the consent agenda staff is recommending items
five through 16 for the consent agenda.
It's my commencement program. Second that, Mickey, second that, a roll call please.
Johnson, list, list. All right, show. All right, item 17, we just dealt with if there are no other questions
we'll move on to item 18, which is authorized mayor of city manager to sign a warranty date conveying
real property located at the addresses listed there. The only thing you want to talk about that,
I'd be very happy to. You'll remember that, and I think it was the end of last year, we entered
to an agreement with the Miami nation to be able to sell, I believe it was roughly 11 acres,
it was immediately adjacent to their tribal properties on Newman Road.
And we did receive permission from the state to be able to sell this directly to the tribe through the
tribal relations act. So at this point, what has taken a little bit of time is that in the block,
this is block eight, the the tribe owns most of it, and then we own the balance of it at about 11 acres.
There were several kind of small strips, there were really utility type easements that were there,
I mean literally maybe 60 feet wide by 100 feet long. The tribe was concerned because obviously once they get this,
they're going to be putting this into a tribal trust. And that if they don't have clear title to the entire block,
it would be very difficult for them. From our point of view, we have the sale of that we've already agreed to,
the numbers that we've already agreed to, but these little strips, basically they have no use to us,
we have no utilities there, it's not quite enough for a road, it's just something that 60, 70 years ago,
in that area was plated, it was plated in, and it's just basically our cake and left over.
So in working with David working with OCAC, what I believe we have right now is an agreement
where the tribe is basically buying the balance of a lot eight is the way it would be working.
So it's basically the same acres that we've already agreed to, it's the same exact price that we've already agreed to,
but they just had to work on the title and OCAC now has the title taken care of.
So we do have a closing schedule on Friday, and this item gives me the authorization to do the closing on Friday,
so we can have this sale, and our hope was to get this done this fiscal year because I already spent this money
buying these little picture of them. So it would be nice to have that in and keep the budget balance.
So I just wanted to report that there was that little hiccup when it came to...
the description because of these little
airant pieces of property that is, again,
have no value to the city whatsoever.
You can't do anything with them.
This property in the city limits, do you?
Yes.
Any questions?
No.
OK.
Do we have a motion to approve?
Motion to approve.
And a second?
Second.
Johnson?
Weston?
High?
Lewis?
Shult?
High?
I did 19.
I don't know.
I can't do property dedication to the city of Miami,
of the following properties.
And there's two, four, six, eight, nine listed, Dean.
You want to talk about that?
Yes.
You'll remember the RIT 66 landing was
proved by the of the Oklahoma Housing Authority Board.
I believe they're talking about upwards of about 16 or 17
senior family homes that have to be within that
half a mile radius of what I call the old Robinson building,
but it's currently used by the Harpens Time Church.
The program using federal housing tax credits
will be converting that building into senior locked apartments,
and then on vacant lots within about a half a mile radius,
they will be building single family homes.
The lots that we are having dedicated from
a model of county are owned by the county,
and they basically agreed to turn them over to us,
and then in turn, we will turn them over to this program
to be able to do in fill.
Now, these aren't the only lots.
These are just the odds of lots on my out of accounting.
And at a later meeting, then we will be turning these lots
plus other lots that we have over to them,
so they can build the single family homes.
But we have to accept the lots from the county,
and that's what this agenda item is tonight.
There's a currently vacant lots.
When you say infill, tell people what they mean by that.
A lot that used to have a house on it,
then over time either was abandoned or destroyed or whatever,
so you see two houses in a vacant lot,
this puts a house in the vacant lot.
This is something that our comp plan has identified
that we need to do in my Amazon.
So that's the exciting thing about this.
We'll start showing people how the infill works.
The older neighborhoods,
starting to reinvest in those neighborhoods,
so you have two, maybe 70-year-old houses,
and then a house that architecturally fits right in the middle,
and having new houses, new life,
brought into these neighborhoods.
It's very exciting.
Okay.
Thank you.
Do we have a motion to approve?
Motion to approve?
Yeah, second.
Second.
Roll call.
Aye.
Lewis?
Johnson?
Aye.
I am 20.
Grand Army of Republic Cemetery,
Mowing Service Contract.
Amendment for, why, 1670.
Yes.
In your packets,
we have a proposal to enter into a contract with
Hopping's Mowing Service.
To mow what we call the big circles out of the cemetery.
Yeah.
In years past, we were fortunate enough that the Parks Department
bishled those for years, and then they started mowing them, and with the
downsizing, they just can't get term anymore.
And actually, that is one of the areas that it actually would be more feasible
to contract that out, because there's nothing in there that,
but any mowing service could hit or tear up while we take care of the
around the monuments in the stone areas there.
Now, I'm a little confused, because we bought a piece of equipment recently, and I thought
that the equipment was for this, is that not mine can.
Okay.
Normal methods.
But what we did is the feasibility study, and said that by the time our personnel
about this large area is what the dance came in at, it was almost double
of what it would actually last, of what it would cost us, so we're a way ahead to
let this get done by the department.
And so that piece of equipment we're buying, what should I do?
It is going to know all the areas of the center, so the other part of the idea
occurs is, I guess.
Yeah, it's plus or minus 10 acres, this area we're wanting to contract out, but the more that
we're wanting to buy is, it will go in rotation to our other mowers and will, because they're
getting up in years and we're wanting to replace them as they get a little age on them.
So, about 88 acres, that would you say?
It's 86 acres, actually.
That's with the monuments.
Yeah, that's everything.
But the property we're looking at, it's rather on 10 acres that we're wanting to contract
out.
That's the north-west.
Yes, it's the north-north-the-end, we call them the big circles.
They're entering in the yellow, actually, outlined in red.
Okay.
And is this?
Mowing service, one that we're currently using, and this is just additional workers as a new vendor
for us.
Yes, Chad does a lot of mowing through our code enforcement.
So if we have to mow, if somebody's we'd laud or something like that and put a lean on it,
we'd go out to bed and I think Chad's service has gotten that quite a bit too, but this is
completely different contract.
Okay.
But we also, we have two vendors that do other large areas, right?
We do in the first apartment.
Right.
We found that we was the most comfortable for us when we send the clothes out to go with Chad.
Okay.
Any other questions?
Does this have to be a period of time?
I don't know.
That's going to be done next week.
Let me just let you all know about that about the three of our months ago.
We actually approved this contract and we've been using the service.
What we're trying to do is get all of our contracts on the fiscal year basis.
So that's why we've come back before you again and asked you to read for this and we can go back for it.
Well, I've been reading the last that I know Brian had some concerns about it and he had questions about it and he's not here tonight.
But if that's okay with it, you might or not find it.
So do we want to table it until next week of the 28th?
Yes Brian is going to be here doing that.
We'll have to.
Okay.
All right. So in the motion to table?
Yes.
I'll second that roll please.
Tonson.
All right.
Shult.
Weston.
All right.
Good.
Thank you.
I didn't want to revise the city of Miami personnel policy sections 4.8.6, 4.9.8.
Again, 5.7.2, relating to overtime compensation paid on actual hours, kid.
Okay.
The FLSA, the Fair Labor Standards Act, requires that employers pay any hours, actual hours worked over 40 at time and a half.
For years, the city has considered vacation, six time, and comp time as actual hours worked.
We're not required to do that per the FLSA.
So we didn't turn a lot at thinking that we've implemented in the last year and a half, very competitive market salaries.
And that this is something we weren't required to do.
When we thought about how to communicate it to employees, I thought Cindy Banner worked him up with the best explanation.
We're just no longer going to pay half time if you take vacations sick and comp time.
So employees are still going to be paid for everything they actually work over 40.
But if you take, for example, made out vacation day and you work a couple of extra hours, those two extra hours will not be time and a half.
They will be straight pay.
And how does this deal with holidays relative to overtime?
We've got a lot of discussion about that and we're leaving that where it is.
So we're still going to consider that when we consider overtime pay, this is only going to involve vacation sick and comp.
It's going to save the city about $25,000 a year.
We're not required to pay overtime pay when there's a holiday in the week, but we choose to.
We chose to, because we felt like it has an additional incentive for employees to work on that holiday.
And in a lot of, in a lot of those situations, you're not choosing to work on that holiday where you might be choosing a specific vacation day sick day, comp day.
And so we really talked a lot about it.
We just felt like we needed to leave the holiday the way it is.
Okay.
Other questions?
We're happy to say the taxpayers money to roll a motion to the proof.
Motion to the proof.
Second.
Welcome.
Thank you.
Question.
For this time.
Sure.
Thank you.
I'm 22.
We're building a proof contract 1674 for street improvements to the lowest in best bid and
my thracity manager and city attorney assigned notice.
How are y'all tonight?
Good.
Sorry Joe couldn't make it tonight.
We went out for bids.
We got two bids on the micro surfacing.
And Bands Brothers was the low bid.
And once we get all their paperwork and bonds and stuff, we just hear tonight to ask y'all
or we can get David and Dean to sign a notice to proceed in.
And so this is, it's giving me work.
It's already been a budget.
Yes.
And we're just opening the bids and, in fact, taking the lowest bid.
We already have done that part.
I have asked Mike if he do.
And Mike wasn't originally ready to do this because I think Joe's going to do it.
We're going to run the slideshow.
But I asked Mike if he could just kind of give us an update on.
Okay.
Not only this project, but some of the other projects that we have going.
Obviously, in my animal, when you say streets, people are interested.
And Mike's ground zero on all that.
And I thought it'd be an opportunity for him to kind of give everybody an update on what we're
up what we're doing right now.
The streets.
So let's go ahead and vote on item 22 then.
And we'll move to the item 23, which is the update.
Do we have the most to approve?
So we have a second.
Second.
Roll call.
Do this.
Question.
All right.
Chances.
It's all yours, Mike.
Okay.
We are at least just going to pull up a Google Earth map here.
Me and Joe has been working in the last couple of weeks.
I'm trying to get a Google Earth map here.
The first one here, she's going to click on the green ones.
That is actually the ones that you all just approve to have the micro ceiling done when everything is done.
It's around seven miles.
I think it's about six point eight miles that they're going to be doing.
We have a map.
Can you kind of describe the streets we're seeing?
Okay.
The long one going up and down there.
That's Elm Street.
That's going to be from the concrete there.
Steve Owens.
All the way to the dirt road to just a little ways past Chris Lane.
Rockdale.
We're going to go from the new bridge.
All the way out to 69A.
We've had these all cracked sealed by the way.
We're going to do good rich from Maine all the way to P Street.
We're going to do a 22nd Veterans.
We're going to go from Maine to H Street.
I can't really see the rest of them.
There's a few other ones that we've gotten done there.
I think H Street's one of them from 9th to 4th.
We're going to do it.
There's just a few other little streets right in there that we're going to do.
That's going to be the ones that they're going to be doing.
As soon as they get everything, we get the notice to proceed.
They're ready to come.
They're talking like within the next week or two.
be here sooner or the better for us and Mike also it's not just going to be the
microcealing but we're also going to be striking them after that we've had a
lot of people asking about our arterials and getting them striped and we've
been holding off on that to do the microcealing and the striped can be
followed. Yes we have we're going to get direct traffic to come in right behind
and they said that could come in just a day or so later and stripe them and
not all I mean Elm Street will stripe that thing from one end to the other
good rich we'll probably do some stripe being there but some of the streets
are one of the streets over there is a it's be Northwest and it's from the
truck or out to one block we probably won't stripe that we'll just put some
stop blocks where the stop signs are at there's not a lot of traffic that runs through
there so not all of them we're going to get complete yellow and white lines and
everything we're going to try to just keep it like it is right now.
Whoa streets we shut down for a time or well the striping or if the
slowy ceiling yeah the streets will be shut down a little bit we're going to try to make
them do like veterans and all that do one lane at a time and go from like
central to a drop-dale do one-lated time like one traffic come through because
there's a drying process on it and they're not going to shut the whole road down
we're not going to allow that we'll do little sections at a time. Main streets one of
them two that we're doing from Steve Owens all the way down to first street north
but they're going to do that last at night or last but there's no way we can
shut that down in the day yeah so and our cracks dealers they did at night as well
too that's why there wasn't a whole lot but there will be some streets shut down
for a little while but I don't know exactly the dry time I want to say this
temperature we're having probably just you know maybe in a higher hour and a half
oh yeah it's yeah it's it don't take long it's just long as soon as the water gets
out of it so the whole of this information on our website well actually we've been
working on this me and Joe getting this going and IT things soon as we get everything
done and lined out they can put it on our website where people can go on there and
look and see what we've done what kind of application we used give us about
through we've working on a three year plan right now as well on this so give us about
three or four more weeks we'll have that and it'll be under future plans so people
could go on there to see what more areas we're doing we're trying to get it all
lined out it's just taking us a little bit any more questions on these
this one here is just some asphalt completed streets that we've done if you'll
notice there the real long one from up to that up and down that's L Street I think
it was the very first year we started the program we milled and paved that and then
we cracked sealed it
Just various streets on there. It looks like main street there downtown towns. We've kind of been milled and paved
It's various streets though. It has to be either them milled and paved or
Have done some overlays on kind of get them back into shape and buy some years on them
This one here the concrete when completed a lot of them are either concrete streets that we had completely reconstructed
There's a few up on there where we just did some concrete panel repair on that block
Just replaced a couple two or three and it was good to go
But a lot of them are the reconstructs that we were doing in concrete
This one here is just some of the maintenance that we've completed
If you'll at the bottom down there that's more at down like Morgan's heel
I think it was the first or second year we started the program. We slurry sealed all of them had I'm painted
Some of them are just some softbubber pairs that we done on that road
But a lot of them was the slurry seal across the river
So it's just different asphalt. I think I think
19th is on there where we overlaid it from B Street to D Street 19th Northwest
It's on there. So just a lot of different maintenance deals that we've done with asphalt
Can you kind of click on all of them? Yeah, I'm kind of giving them an overview
So there's there's kind of a you know, give you an overview of where we've been what all we've done
We're trying to make sure and hit every single area of town do a little bit in each one
Kind of giving it up day right now the contractors had the asphalt are the concrete's been poured in the alley up there on Main Street right now
We're waiting for the concrete break to come back before we can open it up
Probably another two to three weeks before that thing. I'll be ready to go. We'll let the people have it
They've got a completely poured
C Street south west over by the hospital. They've got it dug out and they're rocking it in
I didn't I didn't go by there today. I was actually
out paving with the guys today, but they've been rocking it in they should be moving to sunset strip the end of this week or first of next week
Start digging it out and getting it ready
I got my crew we were out today will be in tomorrow
We're out on the G Southwest out there we put the bottom lift to asphalt on it today
We're gonna try to get the top lift in tomorrow
And then we're gonna move to the little one line here there
22 get that over late. So the contractors kind of you know, not necessarily waiting on us
Please allow us to have a few extra days. We can get that done and everybody can have that you might remember that was a project
Where it's hard for people to get into the neighborhoods who had kind of tied it in such a way that it wouldn't interrupt everything because
Sunset's gonna take a while. Yeah, it'll take them
three, four weeks, maybe a little longer.
It's a really-
I really have a total mileage that all those colored line
represented.
No, I don't.
That's something that I'll be in Joe.
We'll kind of sit back and total mileage of everything
we've done.
Super, we're at 23.
How much?
I've had it one time as over 23 miles.
I've heard that it's about 23 miles.
Yeah, 23.
Yeah, I kind of what I heard.
But now we're getting ready to do this.
Sorry, Sillin.
It's going to add about another seven.
And then the two concrete streets aren't on there yet, either,
because they're not complete.
So...
Mike, can you tell us how things are going with the asphalt
patcher and the way you're doing that?
And also, can you also talk about the project
that we're starting to work on in front of the Coleman on Main Street?
OK.
The dirt patcher, we've been taking it out every Thursday,
and we've been taking a section of town
and trying to patch some of the potholes in that area.
Some areas, we went over here from 9 to 12
and from H to P, in the northwest.
We went over there and started, as a really bad part of town.
It took us like seven days over there just to do that little area.
It don't seem like a very big, but there was a lot.
We went from there, we went over by...
From M Street, walking part to trucker out,
and from Steve Owens, this central,
we were over there in that little area four days.
So we're just trying to hit every little single part of the town
just kind of keep bouncing around and back and forth
so everybody gets a little bit of it.
But we're taking it out every Thursday.
It's working great.
You all probably noticed a lot of them on the trucker out.
We could think about it, those we haven't went back
and had to patch a bunch out on their stadium.
It's good.
Typically, well, way we were doing it.
What we put in there, as soon as it rang, they're gone.
Back we go again.
So it's a really good piece of equipment.
The guys really love it.
We patch it, we don't usually have to go back.
We have found out that there can't be any moisture in the hole.
First moisture in the hole, we're probably not going to stay.
We patched a couple of them that about two days after it rang
and there was a little moisture we couldn't get out of it.
And it didn't last but one rang.
The next rang was gone.
But for the most part, that was a learning curve there.
For two pod holes, everything else was staying good.
Was the other one there?
Main Street.
I'm writing for the Coleman.
Main Street, we're going to try to go in there.
We're going to the two driving lanes.
We're going to saw cut that.
And we're going to tear the asphalt out about three or four inches deep.
It kind of depends on how deep the asphalt comes out.
And we're just going to relay that hole intersection.
But just the driving lanes, not the parking lanes, the parking lanes aren't too bad.
But the driving lanes, we're going to saw cut that tear it out.
And then, lace a new asphalt in there.
We need to get it at least three to four inches deep so that hot asphalt will adhere to
what's underneath it.
We do it any less than that and it probably ain't going to stay again.
And we also hope to be able to do a design.
because with these heavy rains, we continually get it in the CBB office and in the Colman.
And trying to design it in such a way that we can get some of the rainwater away from there.
Yeah, and get it to moving on down.
One of the good things too about that is that we also put a new sidewalk in right across from the news record there.
We did that sidewalk so that people, the handicapped, can get down through there.
We're going to be there, we're going to miss doing that.
We're redoing that intake right there too.
So now we're hoping with all the changes we're doing up there, the intake should be fine.
We actually added about, I think it was seven inches, so we're adding seven inches more capacity in there.
So hopefully that'll help as well.
I think just one of the things to talk about.
We talked about their stream budget, but I want to compliment Mike on this.
He was part of the project when we were talking to everybody in public works.
And also utilities about limited funds and how far we can stretch them.
Mike and Chris both really made a very good case for an additional full-time person.
FTE and those are hard to come by.
But you know, basically what you're looking at is if you could add more FTEs, you can be out and patch and then also do some of these projects much better.
And then we got to solid waste, solid waste indicated that with a new piece of equipment, which is included in the budget,
they could have one person do what now takes three for the commercial and for the commercial collection, just like the residential collection.
So once that piece of equipment's on board, which will take a few months to spec it and get it in, it's not going to be instant.
But those will have two FTEs, then that will be able to put toward water and put towards straight to even increase the amount of hatching and fish.
And that will be the amount of hatching and fixing and everything that we do right now.
So trying to incrementally make improvements as we go.
And that was kind of good to see three departments working together to pull resources to make it happen.
While you're talking about that today, as always out there asphalt in the day,
the right way to how to climb and loan us a couple of guys to haul the asphalt for us.
And Kevin Hornsson, a guy to truck the asphalt for us.
Without their help, we wouldn't have been able to do it.
I only leave me left me one guy out there to drive a truck, so they helped us out big today.
So we're making a good effort.
Mike, Mike, all the time, what are we getting to?
So probably he has nightmares about me, I'm sure.
But I think by and large we're making progress and we're figuring out better places to stretch our dollars.
So I appreciate that.
Thank you.
I don't want to be.
I'm in the ordinance of Mending Code Section 23-101,
which requires a valve and driver's license for the class of vehicle being operated to complain.
with restrictions and prohibiting operations of a motor vehicle when the privilege is suspended or
evoked. Glam-Hara even nicer. Just fine. I think it's fine. I got my body guard here.
I saw it. Yeah, this is pretty much a housekeeping issue. The wording had be omitted at some previous
time in the past and it makes it difficult for the officers to, you know, use the city ordinance.
Whenever they have not a real clear view of what it is that the facts are in the in the case.
And the improvement of this ordinance will basically take out the questions of which jurisdiction
to go to to, you know, file the, you know, the violations. Do you have that front of you? I don't
Okay. Well, delete part of it and add part of it in A, B, and C. And they were good to go.
And these changes will bring us into compliance with the state statute also as that correct?
Yes. Yeah. So make your job easier, make the judge job easier, bring us into compliance with state statute.
That fits in with the current coding. I think that the officers use the control units and the right
presentations. Sure. Yeah. Okay. Any questions for plan? That's right. We have a motion to approve.
Motion to approve minute. And a second. Second. Roll call. Thank you. All right. Thank you, sir.
Hi. How the new business team and new business for the council. He's not new business for this day.
Okay. Mayor and council announcements. Neil, did you have something? Yes, sir. I know we don't have a regular meeting
before the Fourth of July. We have a works on next week. But one of the ways here about a happy
Fourth of July in a safe room a bit last year. I don't know whether in my fellow council members got
complaints last year, but I did. We had complaints of she and fireworks all after the times or before
the times and leaving trash out in the street where they get their fireworks all. I just hope that they
everybody will be respectful of your neighbors and clean up after your mask. I hope we don't have to
revisit this issue. Maybe we will. But I asked Mr. Jim Ellis of mine and he's where he would put something
in the paper about our ordinance and what it says. And I just hope everybody follows that. And she
faffy we want to chime in, you can. Take your love and we'll play back.
and do a good look and it's top of the course that our GP all over.
We do a threshold on my basis.
And I'd ask Chief Klein to speak about some things on our Facebook page
and information about when it's legal and when it's not legal,
we'll set off fireworks in town, so we're going to be taking care of that as well.
And see what we can have.
We'll also re-tose that into our environment.
Okay, thanks, sir.
Thank you.
We're changing only one item.
I just want to confirm that next week on the 28th
that we're going to have a really special meeting.
It's part of what we would have there as our study session,
but also a special meeting.
I think staff probably will just be bringing you just routine items
and with a goal that we would have that meeting on the 28th
and then we will be canceling the regular meeting on the 5th.
So I just wanted to confirm if that's the plan.
We will proceed accordingly.
Okay.
And here's, here's the term special meeting,
but we approve a different schedule.
It's a different schedule.
It's at 4 p.m. for the study session,
but we believe we will, can we add items on that
and call it a regular meeting?
It is a regular meeting because it was a schedule that was approved.
We just always chose to not have any action items
and make a study session.
Now, though, I do have a question about the special utility authority
meeting that would be scheduled on the 5th
that if we cancel that,
can we have a special meeting on the 28th for the special utility authority
for things that they need to take care of?
Yeah.
Okay.
I think everybody would like to have the 5th off.
I don't think you're going to have staff
to complain too much about that.
And we'll call it for immediately following the council meeting.
Yeah.
Right, I'm excited.
Okay.
And that's it.
Item 28 is adjourned.
Do we have a must to adjourn?
Let's adjourn.
And second.
Second.
We'll call.
Question.
All right.